Wenqi Jiang Updated on 7/31/2022

Wenqi Jiang

Data Engineer / Backend Engineer

My name is Wenqi Jiang. I'm a software engineer with 3 years' experience in **big data infrastructure** and **backend services**, specializing in scalability, high availability, and low latency distributed systems design and implementation. I am proficient in Java and Scala. Not only that, but I have learned to use React and Flutter to search for interesting challenges.

Furthermore, I enjoy powerlifting and traveling in my spare time.

Contact:

Mobile: KzM0IDY5MS03NTItMTU3

• Email: jiangwenqi1995@gmail.com

• Online Resume: jiangwenqi.info

• GitHub: github.com/jiangwenqi

• Blog: dev.to/jiangwenqi

Experience

OEG-UPM | Ontology Engineer

Dec. 2021 - Jul. 2022

A student scholarship for the development of linking algorithms and graph linkers.

LOOM-LD

- Analyzed ontologies from different data sources, like DBpedia, Wikidata;
- Specialized 7 linking discovery algorithms, including string-based similarity and geometry relationships;
- Implemented a Sparql-based linking application by using Apache Jena, and evaluated it with the OAEI-2021 datasets;
- Written the master's thesis.

Keywords: RDF, SPARQL, Apache Jena, String-based Similarity, DE-9IM, OAEI

TOGIC | Big Data Engineer

May 2019 - Aug. 2021 · 2 yrs 4 mos

Offline Data Warehouse

- Maintained the Hadoop cluster containing over 200 TB of data, including user and system logs from 3 different sources, which generated 300 GB per day;
- Upgraded big data components, including Hadoop, Spark, Kafka, etc., and monitored them on CDH;
- Designed and implemented a four-layer data warehouse based on the STAR model by using Hive, which had over 150 tables;
- Rewrote the ETL process, which saved over 80% of storage and fixed the small files' problem on HDFS;

Keywords: CDH, Hadoop, Kafka, HIVE, Spark

Data Statistics System

- Restructured the statistics system based on the new offline data warehouse;
- Rewrote the code by using Spark DSL, making it more readable and maintainable;

Wenqi Jiang Updated on 7/31/2022

• Optimized the system's performance, reduced the process time by 25% compared to the previous version;

• Implemented more than 30 new statistical demands and fixed bugs.

Keywords: Sqoop, Hive, Spark, Elasticsearch, MySQL, MongoDB, Scala, Python

Log Collection Service

- Designed and implemented the log collection pipeline using Nginx and Netty, improving performance, stability, and scalability;
- Processed all logs into the Kafka cluster, which has 5 brokers, 3 replications, and 7 days of redundancy, improving robustness.

Keywords: Nginx, Netty, Java, Kafka, HDFS

WEBSTUDIO | Backend Engineer

Jul. 2018 - Apr. 2019 · 10 mos

- Implemented backend APIs of big data visualization dashboards and general reports for the BI applications;
- Developed more than 25 data operators, such as summation, date conversion, string processing etc.;
- Implemented the one-click function of syncing all user information;
- Expanded 16 data sources, including MySQL, SQL Server, MongoDB etc.;
- · Maintained the big data cluster;
- Fixed bugs and developed new features for the previous projects.

Keywords: Dubbo, Spring Boot, MyBatis, Hibernate, Nginx, Docker, FastDFS, CDH, HBase, Impala

KEG-THU | Software Engineering Intern

Feb. 2018 - Jul. 2018 · 6 mos

- · Organized and annotated critical illness insurance documents;
- Trained models to extract the logical structure of insurance documents by using GROBID;
- Created a desktop application using above models;
- Maintained datasets in NoSQL database, like MongoDB, Neo4j;
- · Completed the thesis.

Keywords: NLP, CRF, GROBID, Neo4j, MongoDB, Java FX

Open Source

Dapp Learning DAO

Apr. 2022 - Present

- · Contributed various tutorial tasks;
- Translated the basic tasks;
- Shared the latest blockchain news and cutting-edge technics in the community.

Keywords: Blockchain, Web3.js, Solidity, Dapp, Ethereum, Hardhat, Alchemy, Infura, DAO

Education

- MS Data Science · Polytechnic University of Madrid | 2021 2022
- BE Computer Science & Technology · Beijing Information Science & Technology University | 2014 2018